Matthew Gourd

East Finchley, London, N2 (+44) 7498 719486 mattgourd@gmail.com

Profile

Technical Documentation Manager with over 20 years of experience in digital content creation. Cheerful, enthusiastic, and approachable, with strong communication skills across all levels.

Interests: Fintech, digital banking, cloud banking, digital wallets, loan origination, online payments, e-commerce, payment gateways, money transfer, SaaS, DevOps.

Expertise

- Documentation management
- Technical writing
- People management
- Information architecture
- UX writing

Technical skills

- Docs-as-Code
- Markdown, AsciiDoc, HTML
- XML, JSON, YAML
- OpenAPI, Swagger, Postman
- Git, GitHub, GitLab

Work history

Senior Technical Writer, Backbase - November 2021 to current

Manage and expand functional, procedural, and reference documentation released with a loan origination software product offered to banks.

Improve documentation architecture and style, adhering to the Google developer documentation style guide.

Manage and streamline internal processes with other technical writers and stakeholders to deliver greater efficiency.

Technical Account Manager, Viva Wallet - May 2021 to October 2021

Took ownership of client queries, working independently or co-ordinating with colleagues in Sales Success, Product and Development teams. In the event of platform instabilities, software bugs or loss of service, expedited issues to the Core team.

Wrote and published technical documentation for the Viva Wallet Developer Portal. Established a Docs-as-Code approach with Markdown for content authoring, a static website generator for online publishing, and GitHub for version control.

Role highlights:

- Expanded the developer portal with tutorials, examples, and other enhancements
- Retained two high-value clients through the use of first-class technical help
- Trained and mentored two technical account managers

Technical Writer, Viva Wallet - January 2019 to April 2021

Lead technical writer for Viva Wallet. Developed comprehensive web-based developer resources for payment APIs, online checkouts, and e-commerce plugins.

Role highlights:

- Built a brand-new developer portal from scratch
- Introduced Docs-as-Code approach to documentation
- Enhanced and extended API reference material

Digital Content Officer, UAL - April 2018 to December 2018

Developed online content and forms for the University of the Arts. Helped to migrate content to a new website platform.

Technical Writer, ipagoo - September 2017 to February 2018

Wrote API documentation and technical blog posts for a FinTech in the Open Banking space. Brought in a standardised look to all digital content, and built a developer portal from the ground up.

Technical Writer, MIRACL - June 2016 to May 2017

Contractor at a cyber security startup. Wrote user guides to accompany a zero-factor authentication platform. Peer-reviewed MIRACL SDK developer support material. Tested and documented encryption products on AWS servers and VMs.

Education

The University of Wales - 1994 to 1995

BSc (Hons) Technology Management (one year completed at 2:1 level).

Marling Grammar School - 1990 to 1994

10 GCSEs, seven at Grade C or above; two A-Levels (English and Art).